<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>WARP Blog</title>
        <link>https://broadinstitute.github.io/warp/blog</link>
        <description>WARP Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[WARP Whole Genome and Exome Pipelines Produce Reblocked GVCFs]]></title>
            <link>https://broadinstitute.github.io/warp/blog/Nov21_ReblockedGVCF</link>
            <guid>https://broadinstitute.github.io/warp/blog/Nov21_ReblockedGVCF</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[November 9, 2021]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="november-9-2021">November 9, 2021<a href="#november-9-2021" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to November 9, 2021" title="Direct link to November 9, 2021">​</a></h4><p>We are announcing the latest release of the Whole Genome and Exome production pipelines, which now produce reblocked GVCFs, a compressed form of GVCF files, as default outputs. </p><p>This is a major release, which in this case means:</p><ol><li>The data output from the pipeline is scientifically different than in previous versions.</li><li>Data output from this pipeline should not be co-analyzed with data from previous versions (for example, in joint calling), without first reblocking the GVCFs. </li><li>Users of the pipeline will see a change in both input and output interfaces.</li></ol><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reblocking--what-is-it-and-why-use-it">Reblocking – what is it and why use it?<a href="#reblocking--what-is-it-and-why-use-it" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Reblocking – what is it and why use it?" title="Direct link to Reblocking – what is it and why use it?">​</a></h2><p>Reblocking is a process of compressing GVCFs that reduces file storage footprint and facilitates joint genotyping by removing alt alleles that do not appear in the called genotype. Normal GVCFs contain blocks of adjacent homozygous reference (homRef) genotype calls that are stored as a single entry when they have the exact same value up to a Phred-scaled confidence of 60. The vast majority of downstream analyses discard homRef genotypes with a confidence of less than 20, so we can compress that data without losing any fidelity in downstream analysis. </p><p>Additionally, because most whole-genome sequencing aims for 30X coverage, most confidences are around 90 or higher. With that, we can represent large intervals of high coverage with a single entry, indicating all high-quality homRef genotypes.</p><p>The reblocked GVCFs are sufficient for multiple downstream applications. While some applications, like population variation surveys, can establish variant frequency using binary (i.e. good/bad) homRef confidences, other applications, like de novo analysis, require more nuance. For the latter kind of applications where the reference status of the parents is critical, the reblocked GVCFs provide multiple intermediate categories for homRef confidences. </p><p>Overall, reblocked GVCFs reduce the storage and I/O required to operate on variant data. This leads to faster, more efficient, and less expensive call sets. It is standard practice at the Broad to reblock GVCFs before joint calling. Now, we are making that step a standard part of the GVCF generation in the single sample pipeline. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-is-reblocking-implemented-in-the-pipelines">How is reblocking implemented in the pipelines?<a href="#how-is-reblocking-implemented-in-the-pipelines" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to How is reblocking implemented in the pipelines?" title="Direct link to How is reblocking implemented in the pipelines?">​</a></h2><p>We’ve added reblocking as a default subtask, called “Reblock”, in the WARP <a href="https://github.com/broadinstitute/warp/blob/develop/pipelines/wdl/dna_seq/germline/variant_calling/VariantCalling.wdl" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VariantCalling WDL script</a> which is imported by both the Exome and Whole Genome workflows. The Reblock task performs reblocking by using the GATK tool <a href="https://gatk.broadinstitute.org/hc/en-us/articles/360037593171" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ReblockGVCF</a>. </p><p>While the reblocking option is turned on by default for any pipeline using the VariantCalling task, you can optionally turn it off by setting the <code>skip_reblocking</code> input in the workflows input configuration file (JSON). For example, if you’re working with the Exome pipeline, just add the parameter:</p><div class="language-WDL codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#bfc7d5;--prism-background-color:#292d3e"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-WDL codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#bfc7d5"><span class="token plain">ExomeGermlineSingleSample.BamToGvcf.skip_reblocking": true</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div><p>We recognize that some researchers might want to perform reblocking independent of the Exome or Whole Genome pipelines, so we also created a utility workflow to reblock GVCFs. This pipeline takes in GVCFs produced by the single sample pipelines and outputs equivalently reblocked GVCFs. It is available in both the <a href="https://github.com/broadinstitute/warp/tree/develop/pipelines/wdl/dna_seq/germline/joint_genotyping/reblocking" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">WARP repository</a> and in a Terra workspace, and costs less than $0.02 per genome to run.</p><p>If you’re curious as to whether your WARP pipeline output is a reblocked GVCF, just look at the filename suffix; a reblocked GVCF will have the <code>.rb.g.vcf</code> ending. </p><p>As always, if you have any questions about working with the updated workflows, <a href="https://github.com/broadinstitute/warp/issues" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">file an issue in WARP</a>.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="additional-resources">Additional resources<a href="#additional-resources" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Additional resources" title="Direct link to Additional resources">​</a></h2><p>Learn more about the reblocking tool on the <a href="https://gatk.broadinstitute.org/hc/en-us/articles/4405443600667" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GATK Support website</a>.
Learn more about the reblocked GVCFs in the <a href="https://broadinstitute.github.io/warp/docs/Pipelines/Exome_Germline_Single_Sample_Pipeline/README" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Exome</a> and <a href="https://broadinstitute.github.io/warp/docs/Pipelines/Whole_Genome_Germline_Single_Sample_Pipeline/README" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Whole-Genome</a> Overviews.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>warp</category>
            <category>WDL</category>
            <category>genomes</category>
            <category>exomes</category>
            <category>germline</category>
            <category>joint calling</category>
            <category>reblock</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>